Finding Aid for Eleanor M. Bumgardner papers, 1919-1967
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Eleanor M. Bumgardner papers 1919-1967
Bumgardner, Eleanor M. (Eleanor Margaret)
9 oversize volumes
8 linear feet
85842 Aa 2; AC
Personal secretary to Frank Murphy. Correspondence, newspaper clippings, and printed miscellanea concerning the life and career of Frank Murphy; also scrapbooks, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Eleanor Bumgardner (donor no. 3418 ). Additional materials were received from Eugene Gressman (donor no. 1088 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Eleanor M. "Lady" Bumgardner, a Detroit native, worked as private secretary for Frank Murphy from 1933 until his death in 1949. She was thus associated with Murphy while he held the position of governor-general and high commissioner of the Philippines, governor of Michigan, U.S. attorney general, and Supreme Court justice. After Murphy's death, Bumgardner remained with the Supreme Court as an executive secretary until her retirement in 1961. In 1966, she married Frank S. Wright.
During her residence in Washington, Bumgardner was active in social activities in the city. She has been the legal guardian of a number of wards from various countries. Bumgardner was an avid doll collector and a close friend of Jeanne Dixon.
The Bumgardner papers consist of two major series. The first is made up of Frank Murphy papers, including correspondence prior to July 1949, speeches of Murphy, and clippings and biographical materials. The second series pertains primarily to Bumgardner's activities and includes correspondence after July 1949, a topical file of clippings maintained by Bumgardner, miscellaneous books, clippings, and scrapbooks. There are also several files of photographs, portraits and informal photos, of Frank Murphy and Eleanor Bumgardner.
Subjects:
Bumgardner, Eleanor M. (Eleanor Margaret); Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Philippines--History--1898-1946.; United States. Supreme Court.; United States--Politics and government--1929-1933.; United States--Politics and government--1933-1945.; Michigan--Politics and government--1929-1938.; Michigan--Politics and government--1939-1945.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Bumgardner, Eleanor M. (Eleanor Margaret); Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1901-1910.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1911-1920.
Contributors:
Black, Hugo LaFayette, 1886-1971.; Bowers, Claude Gernade, 1879-1958.; Brown, Prentiss Marsh, 1889-1973.; Darrow, Clarence, 1857-1938.; Dewey, Thomas E. (Thomas Edmund), 1902-1971.; Douglas, William O. (William Orville), 1898-1980.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Ford, Edsel, 1893-1943.; Ford, Henry, 1863-1947.; Ford, Henry, 1917-1987.; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965.; Garner, John Nance, 1868-1967.; Gressman, Eugene, 1917-2010; Kennedy, Joseph P. (Joseph Patrick), 1888-1969.; Lippmann, Walter, 1889-1974.; Marshall, George C. (George Catlett), 1880-1959.; Murphy, George, 1897-1961.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Osborn, Stellanova, 1894-1988.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Stimson, Henry Lewis, 1867-1950.; Stone, Harlan Fiske, 1872-1946.; Wallace, Henry Agard, 1888-1965.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.; Davies, Joseph Edward.; Dempsey, Jack, 1895-1983.; Dreiser, Theodore, 1871-1945.; Farley, James A. (James Aloysius), 1888-1976.; Hull, Cordell, 1871-1955.; Ickes, Harold L. (Harold LeClair), 1874-1952.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; La Guardia, Fiorello H. (Fiorello Henry), 1882-1947.; Lewis, John Llewellyn, 1880-1969.; MacArthur, Douglas, 1880-1964.; Mayer, Louis B. (Louis Burt), 1885-1957.; Patton, George S. (George Smith), 1885-1945.; Quezon, Manuel Luis, 1878-1944.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.; Stone, Irving, 1903-1989--Clarence Darrow for the defense.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Frank Murphy papers
  - Correspondence
    - Undated (Box 1)
    - 1908 1930-June 1945, 31 folders (Box 1)
    - July 1945-July 13-1949, 19 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Supreme Court memos and notes undated (Box 2)
    - Bibliographies of Frank Murphy's speeches 1933-1934, 1949 (Box 2)
    - Speeches
      - Undated 1922-1932 (Box 2)
      - 1933-1935 (Box 2)
      - 1937-1939 (Box 2)
      - 1940-1944 (Box 2)
      - 1945-1948 (Box 2)
    - Biographical material, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Papers concerning Murphy's career
      - 1917-1930 (Box 2)
      - Mayor of Detroit (Box 2)
      - Philippines (Box 2)
        (folder 1 of 5)
      - Philippines (Box 3)
        (folders 2-5)
      - Governor of Michigan, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Attorney General (Box 3)
      - Supreme Court, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Papers concerning Murphy and religion. undated, 1937-1943 (Box 3)
    - Papers concerning Murphy's death 1949 (Box 3)
    - "Frank Murphy as Government Administrator" by Edward Kemp (Box 3)
    - Eleanor Bumgardner's notes on Murphy, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Genealogical material (Box 3)
    - Income Tax records
      - 1937-1943 (Box 3)
      - 1944-1946 (Box 3)
      - 1947-1949 (Box 3)
    - Memorial service March 6, 1951 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Correspondence (Eleanor Bumgardner Wright)
  - Undated July 19, 1949-December 1949, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - 1950-1964, 36 folders (Box 4)
  - 1965 (Box 5)
  - 1966 (Box 5)
  - 1967-1977 (Box 5)
- Other Bumgardner materials
  - Diary, concerning trip abroad with Frank Murphy 1946 (Box 5)
  - Papers concerning personal affairs 1964-1967 (Box 5)
  - Papers concerning gifts to various libraries of Murphy papers and memorabilia 1961 (Box 5)
  - Acceptances May 12, 1962 (Box 5)
- Topical file
  - Benitez, Helena (Box 5)
  - Black, Hugo (Box 5)
  - Buhl, Stasia (Box 5)
  - Bullitt, William C. (Box 5)
  - Burton, Harold H. (Box 5)
  - Clark, Tom. C. (Box 5)
  - Cromwell, James (Box 5)
  - Davies, Joseph (Box 5)
  - Douglas, William 0. (Box 5)
  - Dow, Joy (Box 5)
  - Downey, Morton (Box 5)
  - Dragonette, Jessica (Box 5)
  - Frankfurter, Felix, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Gizycka, Felicia (Box 5)
  - Gonzalez, Mrs. Gonzalo (Box 5)
  - Gressman, Eugene (Box 5)
  - Habsburg, Otto (Box 5)
  - Harding, Ann (Box 5)
  - Hildegarde, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Holmes, Oliver Wendell (Box 5)
  - Hoover, J. Edgar (Box 5)
  - Hughes, Charles E. (Box 5)
  - Jackson, Robert (Box 5)
  - Joachim, Sister Ann (Box 5)
  - Kemp, Edward G. (Box 5)
    folder No. 1
  - Kemp, Edward G. (Box 6)
    folders Nos. 2-4
  - MacArthur, Douglas (Box 6)
  - McLean, Evelyn W. (Box 6)
  - Malcañan (Box 6)
  - Malcolm, George A. (Box 6)
  - Michigan (Box 6)
  - Minton, Sherman (Box 6)
  - Murphy, George (Box 6)
  - Osborn, Chase and Stella, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Osmena, Sergio (Box 6)
  - Peterson, Frank (Box 6)
  - Philippines, 6 folders (Box 6)
  - Quezon family (Box 7)
  - Reynolds, Robert (Box 7)
  - Romulo, Carlos P. (Box 7)
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore (Box 7)
  - Rubinoff, Dave (Box 7)
  - Rutledge, Wiley (Box 7)
  - Shriver, Eunice (Box 7)
  - Spencer, Caroline L. (Box 7)
  - Stover, Ruby (Box 7)
  - U.S. Supreme Court, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - Vanderbilt, Neil (Box 7)
  - Villanova Law School (Box 7)
  - Williams, G. Mennen, 3 folders (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous
  - Clippings concerning Bumgardner (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous speeches (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 5 folders (Box 8)
  - Memorial Books and other volumes 1941-1957 (Box 8)
    - Memorial to Louis D. Brandeis 1942 (Box 8)
    - Memorial to Wiley B. Rutledge 1951 (Box 8)
    - Memorial to Robert H. Jackson 1955 (Box 8)
    - Memorial to Charles E. Hughes 1950 (Box 8)
    - Memorial to Frederick M. Vinson 1954 (Box 8)
    - Memorial to Felix Frankfurter 1965 (Box 8)
    - Memorial to Harlan F. Stone 1947 (Box 8)
    - Addresses of Franklin D. Roosevelt, July 19, 1940-January 20, 1941 1941 (Box 8)
      (autographed by Roosevelt)
    - "Hi Sweetie," 1980 (Box 8)
- Photographs
  - Eleanor Bumgardner
    - Portraits (Box 8)
    - Portraits of friends and associates (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Frank Murphy
    - Early photos to circa 1920 (Box 8)
    - Photos 1920s (Box 8)
    - Photos 1930s-1940s (Box 8)
    - Funeral (Box 8)
  - Portraits of friends and associates (Box 8)
- Scrapbooks
  - Scrapbook concerning European trip 1927 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook concerning personal affairs and Frank Murphy circa 1919-1936 (Volume 1)
  - Scrapbook concerning Frank Murphy 1934-1943 (Volume 2)
  - Scrapbook of Christmas cards 1935 (Volume 3)
  - Scrapbook concerning Frank Murphy 1937-1938 (Volume 4)
  - Scrapbook largely concerning Frank Murphy 1948 (Volume 5)
  - Scrapbook 1957 concerning a trip to Europe and the Far East (Volume 6)
    (unbound)
  - Miscellaneous personal scrapbooks (Volume 7)
  - Miscellaneous personal scrapbooks (Volume 8)
    (continued)
  - Miscellaneous personal scrapbooks (Volume 9)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Selective Index to Correspondents
Black, Hugo Lafayette, 1886-1971.
Undated, Aug. 25, 1937, Mar. 7, 1944, June 23, 1947, June 27, 1949
Bowers, Claude Gernade, 1879-1958.
July 23, 1935, Dec. 9, 1935, Jan.24, 1936, Nov. 5, 1936, Nov. 4, 1937, Dec. 14, 1937, Jan. 26, 1936, May 10, 1938, Jan. 4, 1939, Feb. 28, 1940, Mar. 7, 1945, Mar. 13, 1945
Brown, Prentiss Marsh, 1889-1973.
Nov. 10, 1938, Jan. 19, 1939, Jan. 18, 1941, May 21, 1942, June 10, 1942, Nov. 13, 1942, Jan. 11, 1943, Jan. 8, 1944, Apr. 12, 1944, May 1, 1944
Darrow, Clarence, 1857-1938.
Apr. 20, 1933, May 5, 1933, Aug. 5, 1935, Oct. 9, 1935, Oct. 16, 1935, Mar. 29, 1937, Apr. 3, 1937
Davies, Joseph Edward.
Feb. 3, 1938
Dempsey, Jack, 1895-1983.
July 15, 1939
Dewey, Thomas E. (Thomas Edmund), 1902-1971.
Dec. 21, 1938, Jan. 2, 1939, Jan. 19, 1945, Nov. 9, 1945, July 12, 1948
Douglas, William O. (William Orville), 1898-1980.
Correspondence throughout
Dreiser, Theodore, 1871-1945.
Jan. 17, 1940
Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.
June 21, 1948, July 5, 1948
Farley, James A. (James Aloysius), 1888-1976.
Jan. 18, 1937, Feb. 27, 1940, Mar. 8, 1947, July 3, 1958 [to E.B.]
Ford, Edsel, 1893-1943.
Apr. 22, 1933, July 11, 1933, May 9, 1934, June 28, 1934
Ford, Henry, 1863-1947.
Aug. 1, 1938, Dec. 2, 1938
Ford, Henry, 1917-1987.
May 2, 1944, May 31, 1944, June 9, 1944, Apr. 8, 1947
Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965.
Undated, Feb. 12, 1937, July 1, 1937, Nov. 10, 1938, Nov. 23, 1936, Aug. 1939, Nov. 15, 1939, Nov. 18, 1939, Apr. 12, 1941, June 2, 1941, Jan. 26, 1942, Dec. 12, 1944, May 7, 1945, Mar. 8, 1946, Nov. 3, 1946, Nov. 6, 1946, Dec. 27, 1948, Jan. 30, 1949, Apr. 22, 1949, June 4, 1949
Garner, John Nance, 1868-1967.
Jan. 20, 1939, Nov. 22, 1940
Gressman, Eugene, 1917-
Correspondence throughout
Hull, Cordell, 1871-1955.
Nov. 10, 1938, Jan. 4, 1940
Ickes, Harold L. (Harold LeClair), 1874-1952.
Apr. 3, 1939, Nov. 17, 1939, Mar. 18, 1940, Feb. 23, 1946
Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.
Oct. 29, 1947
Kennedy, Joseph P. (Joseph Patrick), 1888-1969.
July 15, 1935, Sept. 4, 1935, Mar. 25, 1938, Feb. 10, 1939, Mar. 17, 1939, Mar. 20, 1939, Apr. 5, 1939, Apr. 17, 1939, May 10, 1939, Jan. 7, 1940, Jan. 8, 1945, Jan. 3, 1946, Apr. 8, 1947, June 14, 1948, Mar. 23, 1961 [to E.B.]
La Guardia, Fiorello H. (Fiorello Henry), 1882-1947.
June 5, 1942, Jan. 7, 1943
Lewis, John Llewellyn, 1880-1969.
Undated [to E.B.]
Lippmann, Walter, 1889-1974.
Jan. 8,1940,Jan. 16,1940,Jan. 23,1942
MacArthur, Douglas, 1880-1964.
Dec. 5,1935,Feb. 7,1945
Marshall, George C. (George Catlett), 1880-1959.
Apr. 15, 1942, Apr. 20, 1942, Apr. 25, 1942, May 18, 1942, June 10, 1942, July 15, 1942, May 10, 1943, May 26, 1944
Mayer, Louis B. (Louis Burt), 1885-1957.
Feb. 12, 1937, Sept. 8, 1944
Murphy, George, 1897-1961.
Correspondence throughout
Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860
Correspondence throughout
Osborn, Stellanova, 1894-1988
Correspondence throughout
Patton, George S. (George Smith), 1885-1945.
Feb. 3, 1945
Quezon, Manuel Luis, 1878-1944.
Jan. 12, 1944
Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.
Oct. 9, 1940, Apr. 19, 1945, July 28, 1958 [to E.B.]
Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.
Dec. 16, 1935, Dec. 23, 1935, Nov. 21, 1936, Dec. 28, 1937, Oct. 5, 1938, Nov. 11, 1938, Nov. 29, 1938, Dec. 2, 1938, Jan. 18, 1939, Apr. 4, 1939, Dec. 9, 1939, Dec. 25, 1939, May 14, 1940, May 15, 1940, June 10, 1940, July 8, 1940, Nov. 22, 1941, Dec. 16, 1941, Dec. 17, 1941, Mar. 16, 1944, Nov. 20, 1944, Dec. 7, 1944, Dec. 15, 1944, Nov. 6, 1945
Stimson, Henry Lewis, 1867-1950.
July 10, 1942, Aug. 8, 1942
Stone, Harlan Fiske, 1872-1946.
Aug. 30, 1943, Nov. 1, 1943, Mar. 2, 1945
Stone, Irving, 1903-1989--Clarence Darrow for the defense.
Apr. 8, 1940, Nov. 9, 1940
Wallace, Henry Agard, 1888-1965.
Sept. 11, 1936, Apr. 8, 1946
Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-
Correspondence throughout